咁誒。
達至目標收入嘅水平。
部咧係引入咧係以其目。
我相信大家都記得咧，就係保監局喺。
二零一六至一七年財政年度嘅預算。
喺去年嘅十月成立，咁咧都係咧係誒。
我哋亦都希望盡量係誒，朝着呢個目標去做嘅。
自律規管機構監管保險中介人，同埋實行中介人嘅發牌制度。
誒，我請保監管局嘅代表誒，首先誒鄭無柱博士作一個簡介。好啊，鄭博士。
繼續開始呢個會議嘅下邊第三個誒第五個項目，就係獨立保險監管局。
政府當局係之前提供咗一份文件，係立法會編號CB固一九八七縮十五至十六零四號文件。
咁根據嘅條例咧，就保監局需要每年度嘅收支預算係提交誒財政司司長咧係批准，咁亦都將預算咧係提交畀立法會嘅會議上高審覽。
多謝主席，各位議員早晨。誒，非常之高興，今日係出席誒立法會嘅財經事務委員會，係同各位介紹保監局二零一六至二零一七年度嘅財政預算案。
整個過程咧係希望能夠平穩過渡，啊，由現時嘅誒政府嘅保監處咧係平穩過渡到去保監局，亦都希亦都係分階段咧係將嗰個誒接手誒三個。
備以及訂立內部行政同埋財務制度等等。
開支嘅四億五千萬元嘅撥款，預算開支咧就大約係一億。
年底之前可以上任，就可以協助保監局開展下一個階段嘅工作。
裏邊唔同範疇嘅誒主要人士，以及咧其他相關領域嘅專業人士。
誒，而家以下就係請委員提問嘅。係由於時間有限咧，我哋都係仍然保持每位議員就係四分鐘嘅連問連答。第一位陳建邦議員。
現行嘅規管制度嘅規管制度咧，係能夠順利到至誒過渡到新嘅架構。誒喺度咧，我係願意咧係誒解答各位議員嘅問題。多謝各位，多謝主席。好，多謝鄭博士。
除咗籌備工作之外，保監局嘅主要職能亦都包括促進保險業市場嘅可持續性，誒保險誒保障保單持有人嘅利益，同埋提升行業喺全球保險業嘅市場嘅競爭力。
誒，例如消費者事務合規同埋會計等等，我哋過去幾個月咧係不斷係與業界溝通，希望更加深入瞭解業界嘅期望同埋佢哋嘅需要，並且向業界表明一個穩健監管制度嘅重要性。
誒左右主要係用嚟係支付員工嘅開支，同埋辦事處嘅租金，同埋有關嘅誒其他嘅開支等等。餘額大約係三億五千萬咧，係作為營運嘅儲備金，係用作誒保監局成立初期營運所需要經費。
應憲法案委員會嘅意見咧，政府亦都承諾咧喺呈交保監局週年嘅財政預算畀誒財政司司長批準之前咧，係保監局咧係會誒就議議嘅財政預算咧向向誒財經事務委員會係作一個簡報。
保監局誒，亦大，我相信大家都會瞭解知道咧，就係我哋要循序漸進嘅方式咧，係從保單嘅徵費、收取保險公司嘅授權費，同埋保險中介人嘅牌照費咧，同埋特定嘅服務嘅使用費咧，係誒按。
保監局嘅運作首年度咧係將會誒誒入不敷支，因因此需要政府嘅撥款。保監局二零一六一七年嘅預算收入為四億五千七百八十萬元，當中亦都包括早前獲得立法會批准用作保監局首兩年營運開。
保監局喺誒二零一六一七年度嘅主要嘅工作咧，就係順利去接管保監處嘅法定職能，同埋展開其他嘅籌備嘅工作，包括分階段招聘主要人員，誒租任辦公室、採購辦公室同埋誒資訊科技嘅設。
喺招聘人員方面嚟講咧，就誒顧問嘅預計，保監局整個團隊初期大約係有二百九十九名嘅員工。參考咗保監處現時嘅架構咧，我哋將會分四個階段。首先咧係聘用一百八十個員工，希望主要員工喺本年。
仲有咧，係提高社會大眾對保險產品同埋保險業嘅瞭解。我哋都成立咗兩個業界嘅諮詢委員會，分別咧係就長期業務同埋一般業務嘅事宜咧，向保監局提供意見。兩個委員會嘅成員咧，包括來自保險業裏。
好，下一位李卓人議員。
意見可以同我哋分享下咧，噉樣啊？啊，鄭主席，好，主席。
即係保險product，我最近咧有個投訴咧，就有個product叫Evergreen。
初初定立咗而家我哋將來發展嘅嘅路向，我相信咧都係朝着你頭先講嗰個誒路向，就係話，希望能夠讓業界能夠保持到有可持續發展嘅一個方向。
嚇，即係差唔多，即係五五年回本，十年有錢賺。咁但係咧時間又過咗去啦，然後跟住咧就發現咧就唔係五年回本，十年都未回本，要十二年先回本。
誒主席，即係我諗誒頭先，陳建波講話，即係希望，即係誒好似少監管啲噉，我就好擔心啊。即係其實我我想問一樣嘢，我唔係關，即係我最關心嗰啲product而家。
啊，嚟緊一年裏邊咧，我相信咧，我哋工作都係誒主要集中係喺嗰個誒人手嘅誒招聘，誒亦都咧係嗰個大家都知道咧，個時間係唔係好非常之充裕，但係我哋都會誒，我同埋我七位嘅保監嗰個成員咧，都會努力確保。
係多謝主席。誒，今日阿鄭慕智主席喺度咧，我哋係首先代表保險界咧，係多謝阿主席咧對呢個保險界嘅承諾同埋努力啦。噉我哋保險界咧對阿鄭主席係好大嘅期望嘅，即係包括希望將來嘅獨立保監咧係唔會過分監管啦，係希望咧即係你知保險界由一個廿二三十年都係有一個自律。
機制咧過渡到一個監管嘅機制咧，噉我希望咧就係係逐步漸進嘅嚇，就唔會咧係即係太過快啦，咁令到業界咧係有一個適應啊，同埋令到咧係中小型嘅公司咧可能個生存嚇，咁先至可以令到市民多啲選擇。因為如果淨係大公司冇中小型公司，對嗰個市民嘅選擇方面都唔係一個。
保持啦，咁業界都好擔心咧。保監督對保公司嘅收費咧，會越嚟越犀利啦，嚇不斷增加。所以咧，將來我希望啊，我相信啊，主席都會做到咧，就係會咧係控制開支啦，應使則使啦。咁文件咧亦都提到咧，就係話咧，保監局會着手同埋各方面研究點樣促進保險業嘅可持續發展嘅啊，例如咧。
係研究金融科技應用帶來風險同機遇，噉我哋當然好高興，即係將來阿主席都都好清楚睇到咧，即係唔係淨係監管，而係監管發展係平衡嘅嚇。噉我希望阿主席都可唔可以講講喺呢一方面，即係喺發展方面，誒頭先啦，包括頭先話應使則使啊，即係成個大嘅方向啊。阿主席有咩可以有咩？
誒，首先咧，第一咧就係我我我喺唔同嘅誒同業界嘅溝通之中咧，我都誒同大家分享咗。我認為監管咧同埋嗰個發展咧係要做一個適當嘅平衡，同埋咧就係行業做得好咧，根本上監管機構咧。
係唔需要誒花一啲咁誒重嘅誒資源咧去去做監管工作。大家都知道，一逢親要做一啲誒點講啊，採取一啲嘅誒紀律措施嘅話咧，就一定係會好長時間同埋，亦都係花費好多嘅費用嘅。咁所以咧，我期待咧。
係能夠同業界咧係一齊去提升佢哋嘅專業嘅水平，同埋佢哋喺誒喺嗰個叫道德嘅商業道德嘅標準。希望佢哋能夠越做越好。我哋都儘量希望咧係誒監管嘅工作咧係係要做到一個合理嘅平衡，就千祈唔好。
係誒，亦都我亦都同業界分享過咧。我話：如果要淨係做監管嘅工作咧，係根本上唔需要成立一個保險監管局嘅。保險監管局另外一個好重要嘅工作咧，實際上咧就係要同業界一齊去點樣去謀求一個新嘅發展嘅路向。咁喺
呢度咧，響可以同各位議員分享咧，就係喺最近一次我哋嘅會議嘅時候，我哋已經決定成立一個成立一個嘅task force，一個工工作嘅小誒工作團隊咧，係同業界一齊去研究點樣樣去為保險業嘅未來咧，係從唔同嘅角度咧去探討噉我。
由保監處咧係喺保險嘅角度，喺喺嗰個誒誒符合嗰個誒我哋嘅指引十六嗰個角度咧，係去睇清楚之後，然後先正提交畀誒證監會咧，係去再作審批。下一位梁繼昌議。
即係根本講到個不保證收益好高都得嘅，但係冇意思㗎。噉你依方面，但係我聽我我亦都打過去你哋啊保監嗰邊，就係話依方面你哋唔諗住監管個product嗰個，但係你會監管個透明度啫。
我相信呢個咧喺喺短期內咧，我哋會誒成立同埋咧係讓業界咧係參與。咁希望透過大家嘅努力咧，係能夠將香港咧係喺嘅保險業嘅發展上邊咧，能夠達到一個真係能夠同香港作為一個國際嘅金融中心匹配嘅一個嘅地位。噉我覺得呢個工作係更加。
更加重要，仲有一個工作，我認為係更加重要咧，就係令到令到誒誒市民大眾對保險業界嘅認識更加重要咧，係讓年青一代認識保險業嗰個嘅專業性咧，係從而令到佢哋係願意去投身入呢個行業嘅。咁呢幾樣咧都係我哋開會。
噉我唔知你有冇聽過咁Evergreen嘅product咧，就係點樣樣咧？就係佢有個guarantee income，有個non guarantee income。李源最好全部用中文。係啊，即係一個保證嘅入收入，同埋一個冇不保證的收入。噉你睇完不保保證同加加埋不保證咧，夾埋就好靚嘅。
噉就因為佢嘅即係不保證收入咧，就即係畀佢趕時講咧，就預期跌咗好多。噉我哋覺得噉樣樣就好差嘅，即係你你氹人落搭就用一個不保證收入氹人落搭，然後跟住最最後咧就原來係唔做唔到喂，噉佢可以咧？
但係透明度嘅監管，我覺得係即係即係有時係係好容易咧，係啲消費者係真係就咁落咗搭啊。就算你話透明度噉，但係褪咗佢啦。咁點解你哋唔可以監管個product嚇？即係嗰啲計數出嚟，你都要睇啊！即係好啦，你話誒誒成條數到底你點樣去？
講到嚇，依個product本身個誒guarantee誒，即係保證收入同不保證收入點樣計出嚟？你哋會唔會監管咧？嚇誒產品監管。O.K.誒，主席各位議員，我相信大家都瞭解咧。而家喺嗰個誒disclosure，即係嗰個嗰個嘅披露方面嚟。
講咧係由證監會係負責去做呢個審批嘅，咁所以咧就係誒，但係如果大家都瞭解知道咧，就誒保監處咧亦都定咗一個嘅誒指引，一個第十六號嘅指引裏邊好清晰講到明咧，係有投資成分嘅保險產品類。
裏邊咧喺個銷售個過程裏邊咧，係要有一啲基本嘅誒符合嘅條件嘅，包括咗例如頭先講即係話非保非保證、非擔保性嘅一啲嘅誒嘅嘅誒嘅嘅產品咧嘅嘅披露嘅呢一方面，咁嗰個咧喺引入咗呢一個。
嘅誒誒指引十六號之後咧，嚇其實個市場個情況，呢啲產品嘅情況咧係已經有，誒按我嘅瞭解咧係已經係有好大嘅好大嘅改變。至於你講嗰個個別嘅產品咧，我因為我唔熟悉，所以好難，亦都唔方便我哋喺作一個。
個誒個別產品個個睇法，不過業界都有畀我哋嘅瞭解，就係話其實將來咧喺嗰個監管方面嚟講咧，係我哋點樣同誒從證監會誒證監會咧係一齊去一齊去大家去睇嗰個嘅監管嘅情形係點樣樣，大家瞭解咧就即係誒我。
就係依家賣保險產品咧，我知道要錄音嘅，但係其實我哋做議誒第一線議員之後，好多投訴咧，就係一啲非投資性嘅純保險嘅嘅嘅產品嘅銷售咧，其實都有好多糾紛嘅。
仲有時間，你哋嗰個人手啦，即係你哋個bench marking啦，你哋招聘嗰個人工水平係同邊一個監管機構去去bench marking？係咪同誒證監會話同有冇啲機構咁bench marking嘅？唔該啊，簡短答。
求要佢要要有某啲嘅資歷，等等呢啲我我都係擔心嘅。主席即係嗰陣時雷曼事件咧，佢經驗話畀我聽咧，好多銀行買雷曼都唔知乜嚟嘅，上嚟即係解到即係即係，所以呢個問題係我哋相誒相當擔心嘅。另外一個附帶嘅問題咧。
作為誒證監會嗰個嘅程序嘅誒監控嘅panel嘅主席咧，我哋亦都要跟進過呢啲誒有投誒，即係有有有有叫投資性嘅誒保險產品嗰個審批嘅過程裏邊咧，係我哋覺得咧係誒而家都有個好嘅改良。大家都知道咧，就首先咧由由。
啊！主席，我本來都唔想問個Eliar嗰樣嘢，即係個誒有投資性產品嗰個保險產品嗰個審批。不過咧，既既然啊阿Moses咧就講開啦，我我想問一問，而家其實誒有有投資性嘅保險產品，而家喺喺三方面喺個設計，喺嗰個風險披露同埋。
銷售呢三個層面嗰度，誒，證監同保監其實即係而家嘅分工係點樣樣咁？如果你覺得而家嘅分工係有缺陷嘅時候，你啊將來會點樣改進呢一個嘅規管咧？呢樣產品嘅嚇嗱，我我相信咧就誒。
喺呢一個喺呢一刻呢個時間咧，係我哋完全未有有足夠嘅人手去做呢件工作，亦都喺嗰個保監嗰個誒會上高咧，係我哋未人討論過呢件事嘅，所以冇辦法今日同你哋分享。我相信日後我哋一定有機會同大誒同你誒誒誒去去再跟。
進呢個問題，但係我似乎覺得一樣嘢就係，始終我哋誒覺得咧就係誒有兩個唔同嘅監管機構咧，我哋一定要去理順咗嗰個監管，大家嗰個嘅誒責任。咁同埋亦都喺誒，我相信大家都睇到咧，就喺嗰個誒誒指引十。
六個裏邊咧，你就好清楚睇到其實保監處同埋將來嘅保監局，我哋睇嗰個層面咧，就係喺銷售，即係話我哋代理人去銷售嘅層面，同埋喺嗰個誒披露嘅層面咧，係我哋都有一啲嘅誒指引，但係實際上呢個披露足。
唔足夠咧，係證監會嗰個嘅誒權力範圍裏邊，所以誒兩個監管機構咧，我相信誒而家嗰個嘅合作咧，係比以前係更加誒更加誒點講啊？大家都配合得比較誒更加好，因為一逢親一個新嘅產品嘅出現咧，一定要有有初初出現嘅時候。
一定有問題，但係我相信咧，就誒大家都知道。不過最後一點，我想提出咧，就係即係其實做投資產品裏邊咧，有好多時候係即係嗰個風險咧，係唔係淨係可以喺個披露文件裏邊嚟睇。所以我哋都睇到咧，我哋有個責任係去做一啲公眾教育嘅嘅。
嘅嘅工作咧，係從而讓到想買呢樣誒誒誒產品嘅人咧，係能夠清晰知道自己嗰個誒行入去做緊啲咩事幹，同埋咧係誒，希望能夠佢哋更加充分去了解，同埋亦都係佢有問題嘅時候有有有適當嘅機制。
咧去去答回覆佢個問題，咁從而令到佢係作一個誒有誒有認識嘅一個嘅決定啦。係啊，主席，即係其實我諗我諗睇到呢個方向就話喺個產品設計風險披露咧，我諗基本上可能都係多啲誒證監會嗰個權力範圍底下嘅嘅事情啦。
但係銷售手法咧，就可能係誒保險公司嗰啲從業員嗰個，亦都係保監局嗰個權力範圍。但係咧，我我就想提醒一點咧，嚇啊啊啊啊啊啊！鄭主席就係話咧誒，好多保險業從業員對於嗰個保險產品啊，咁梗係即係好多知識啦。但係對於投資啊、風險，
啲。
噉啊！佢哋要負責㗎。
保監嘅工作咧，我哋好好期待啊！
噉佢哋係即係嗰三個自律機構。
已經係放開咗畀大家問到好多嗰啲誒監管政策嘅問題，就係今日嗰個。
佢咧，我係可以即係取消嘅。咁誒，亦都咧就係話喺嗰個銷售嗰陣時咧，其實而家我哋係設計咗一張嘅誒誒書面嘅一啲嗯。
因為咧，我哋都收到唔少嗰啲即係投資相連嘅個案，亦都而家仲有啲處理中。噉啊，嗰以前嗰三個所謂叫自律機機構咧，我希望啊啊主席，將來你哋有資源啊！
噉我投訴嗰啲居即係嗰啲誒苦主走嚟揾我，咁咪投訴啦。噉我於是話咧，不如我要求佢見面，同你去陳述個個案，聽下得唔得？佢居然答覆冇冇呢個安排。
做幾多嘢啊嘛，係嘛？嗱，當然啦，而家政府撥億嗰撥誒四億，我記得好似已經係比最初誒喺泛委員會嘅時候嘅承諾係多嘅。噉我哋都係會支持，因為咧，實上我覺得咧就嗰個。
嗰三個治罪機構以前聽到即係處理過個案都好啦，就算你哋未必有權去處理翻都好啦，你都應該要去聽下佢哋嗰啲所謂苦主嘅申訴，理解佢啲乜嘢。咁好多嗰啲咧，我最近有個經驗，即係有啲即係bitter嘅經驗，即係唔係幾好嘅經驗。
啲回報嗰度咧，可能咧就缺乏咗一啲嘅嘅認知，我嘅感覺就係我希望咧，你哋貴谷同誒證監會希望喺長遠嚟講都要對呢一批嘅嘅嘅，即係從事呢啲啊產品嘅銷售嘅嘅同事咧，係提高佢嘅培訓。啊，第二樣嘢咧，我我。
嗱，我我相信咧嗰個誒嗰個誒benchpark咧，唔係單一個機構嘅咯嚇，即係我哋會睇曬一般嘅監管機構嘅綜合症嘅。O.K. 下一位何俊仁議員，我都想同啊鄭主席咧跟進，即係正話所講嗰個對於投資產品嗰個。
個誒銷售嘅監管咁咧就誒，其實而家好多嘅保險產品話就係保險，其實可能係好少成分保險，好大成分係投資產品。其實嗰啲嘢應該就喺銀行賣，或者係經過一啲即係嗰啲證券經紀賣嘅。就我即係而家就嚟咗去保險當保險產品賣咁咧，就雖然我哋所關心問。
第一就係就係誒，即係保監同埋證監之間嗰個規管嘅標準係咪基本上個控制嚇咁呢？呢個第一樣嘢。第二樣就係大家啲從業員，大家個要求個水平係咪一致嗱？你知道咧，如果做保險以往傳統嘅從業員咧，就係最緊要了解嗰啲。
誒賣賣嗰啲誒誒保單啦，即係真係保險嗰啲啦。其實嗰度已經好多學問喺度㗎啦，嗰度相當多嘅學問要。依家但係問題咧，你而家原來賣嘅嘢咧，原來就少少部分係係保險，大部分係投資。噉佢哋啊，對嗰啲投資嘅嘢有幾多嘅認識？有冇足夠嘅誒誒誒要求？
個糾紛係在於佢解釋嗰個問卷嘅時候，好多時候講得唔清楚嘅，邊啲嘢需唔需要披露，有邊啲疾病，你有咩健康嘅歷史，好多時候咧就喺解嗰度嘅時候咧就誤導咗嗰個買買單嘅人，咁又跟住嗰張單係冇效啦，原來以前做嗰個好少嘅手術等等嘅嘢，咁咧於是乎咧就拗到好犀利，噉。
咁呢個其實要埋錄音係咪應該嘅咧？噉就有冇研究呢個問題嚇？啊嗱，誒主席，我相信咧就誒大部分嘅問題咧，我一間需要請阿Eddie幫手答，因為我我相信我我未人有足夠經驗可以講到話，即係喺嗰個總淹從業員喺嗰個銷售過程裏邊過去，我哋嘅嘅經驗係。
點樣樣？但係，我覺得你頭先提嗰個就話，即係誒保保監局同埋將來喺證監會嗰個嘅大家相會嘅誒工作嗰個嘅層面咧，我相信一定要誒，一定要大家協調好，同埋係誒要大家個分工會做得更加更加好。呢個我。
我相信咧係無可置疑，我哋會向著呢個方向走。咁第二咧，我我瞭解咧，就現時要銷售有啲有投資性產品嘅誒保險從業員咧，喺佢哋嗰個誒自願監管嘅嘅制度裏邊咧，已經有要求到要買呢啲嘢嘅人係有有一個。
特誒更加深入嘅培訓，讓佢哋瞭解清楚，知道嗰啲嗰啲誒產品呢嘅嘅情形，從而咧係亦都知道佢哋嗰個嘅責任去去做點樣喺銷售嘅過程裏邊，佢自己嘅責任。咁不過咧，當然咧係誒喺一個行業裏邊咧，係一定係良莠不齊嘅，一定會有。
係。
嗯。
當然，你哋係要向前看，睇新嘅個案。
但係咧，你唔可以唔去睇翻呢啲咧，起碼誒。
鄭主席同埋有關同事，好，多謝。噉啊，我哋就到下一，咦？陳建波想做第二個問題。
你嗰啲嘢咧，將來啊，你哋做堵塞佢啲漏洞咧，有有有咩嘅？當然，我梗係希望你哋啦。就算你哋做唔到誒誒，即係所謂回溯。
啊！即係冇陳述個安排，OK，我解個個案畀你聽啫，冇呢個安排。噉你諗下咧，你即係即係即係而家已經。
你講翻都無謂啦，因為點解咧？因為點解要成立呢個保監咧？就係根本以前嘅制度好，即係好不堪，可以咁講。咁但係咧，主席，我希望咧，你喺嘅你嘅資源控制上面咧。
嚟提升咧，係從而讓到佢哋咧係能夠做得更加好，從而就唔需要去去去做誒監管同埋去去做一啲誒紀律處分嘅工作啦。好，我諗嗱，議員咧就已經。
仲係有苦主投訴緊嘅個案，你都係盡量去畀喺你嘅資源許可之下咧，最少聽佢哋個個案，理解佢哋乜嘢，未必一定你權力範圍裏邊咧，你哋嘅執法機構可以做到啲嘢，但係從呢啲咧，你見到佢哋嗰啲。
effect effect都好啦，追索力都好啦，你哋能夠篤得幾多都好啦，其實都應該要影響下佢哋嘅噉嘅樣，嚇，即係有好多公司佢哋都係誒大老闆就做呢一個，即係老闆就坐埋嗰啲即係監管機構都有，嚇，即係利益角色均突嘅嚇。
啊，未必係做到最最足位都做到最好。噉我相信咧，將來喺監管嘅工作裏邊嘅時候咧，做得唔好嗰啲或者違規嗰啲咧，我哋能夠好快脆係處理到嘅話咧，噉我相信咧，對對對，消費者嘅保障係一定會提升。全部要求錄音嗰度，你唔好答到我錄音。我相信呢個係要請啊。
O.K. Eddie畀啲經驗同大家分享啦，好嘛？簡短。係誒，主席或者我喺度補充一下啦。咁其實喺過去兩年咧，保監處已經係發出咗即係頭先啊，主席提到嘅指引十五同埋指引十六。指引十五咧就係關於一啲同誒投資相連有關嘅長期保險嘅一啲保單嘅，而指引十六咧就一啲冇誒投資相連。
嘅一啲長期保單咧都要誒有一啲即係誒要加強佢嗰個管理嘅。咁誒呢一啲指引咧最主要咧就係話喺銷售嗰陣時咧就住呢個投資雙年嗰陣時咧，除咗頭先話要錄音之外咧，仲係有個冷靜期嘅。咁即係喺呢個冷靜期之內咧，如果嗰啲顧客咧係唔即係覺得呢個保誒誒產品係唔適合。
嘅一啲聲明咧，就係話要嗰個誒中介人咧，就同嗰個顧客咧，就要逐項咧係睇一睇，佢哋明明白佢嗰啲風險啊、收費啊，同埋就係話喺誒一啲誒誒收費啊，同埋佢如果係斷單嗰陣時咧，嗰啲賠償啊嘅各樣嘢嘅，噉佢要嗰個簽名。時間夠啦，就因為誒我。
聚焦咧，應該係財政安排嘅。咁大家如果有關心嘅咧，就稍後有機會咧，我哋再作其他嘅安排畀大家溝通。好，最後一位係善眾街員朱定，我知道當然係呢一個問財政嘅問題啦。咁但係財政問題咧，事實上就睇你畀幾多錢你哋，你哋可以。
人員入場。
港交所。
噉我依度咧就。
幾六啊五啊，甚至更加高啦，令到多啲人咧係可以。
噉我哋進入第六個項目，就係。
九九四縮十五至十六零四號文件。
噉我哋而家係請咗誒當局方面咧嘅。
政府當局咧，亦喺會議上咧提供咗一個簡介嘅資料畀大家嘅。
嘅代表啊，戴林漢先生以及有關其他幾位嘅同事出席。
上市公司環境、社會及管治披露規定嘅個項目，噉我哋請有關嘅誒。
簡單講講呢個文件嘅背景，呢一項嘅議程係李卓人議員建議作出嘅討論嚟嘅，係政府當局喺會議前咧提供咗一份文件，係立法會C.B.括弧一。
啊！鄭主席，誒誒，主席嘅各位議員，我好多謝啊！誒，議員提嘅嘅意見，我哋會記錄啊，我哋亦都會提入。噉就誒喺過去嗰幾個月，我同業界嗰個嘅誒即係嘅交流之中咧，亦都瞭解到一樣嘢咧，就係其實處理呢啲投訴案件咧，就
係誒，相當之反覆嘅，亦都喺誒。佢哋其中一位嘅提出咧，就話現時嚟講咧，有最低限度有七個至八個唔同嘅渠道咧，係投訴同一個案件。噉佢希望我哋將來咧係喺監管局嘅層面咧，係能夠即係理順咗呢呢一個嘅投訴機制咧。
從而更加有效同埋有效率地去去去去處理啲投訴。噉我我覺得呢又都係一個好好嘅建議啦。咁將來希望能夠即係監管局有足夠嘅資源去做呢樣工作。咁但係誒誒誒，作一個合理嘅平衡係我哋誒，我哋永遠都要。
要做嘅工作嚟嘅，我哋唔會話係偏重喺邊一方面嘅工作，而實際上監管同埋去發展嘅業誒誒誒嗰個行業咧，都係一同等嘅重要。咁所以咧，我相信咧就，但係我頭先嘅期望咧，就係希望能夠真係將嗰個業界嗰個嘅專業嘅水平。
嘅基本上嘅問題咧，都睇嚟都係圍繞住希望你哋省靚嘅招牌啊，用好資源就提中提高公眾對保險嘅信心。噉啊，我就唔特別再提問題啦，因為時間都超咗啦，所以我做主席我都係慳翻幾分鐘畀大家。噉啊，多謝啊！
我諗嗱，好簡短啦，好簡短啦，好啊，好簡單啊。嗱，文件咧又講今年會請一百八十人啦。咁但係獨立保監其實要幾年先全面操作啊。咁嗰人手亦都未必可以即刻需要全面配備嘅。噉我想問咧，就因為可能你請嗰啲人好多都係有保險經驗㗎嘛。咁但係而家業界正正又缺乏呢啲人才。噉我想了解下咧，主席，如果你遇到嘅情
情況就係話你扯走咁多人啊，即係我諗業界都好睏難，可能會噉。所以，我諗會唔會係考慮下啲方方法係分階段請啦？呢個第一啦，重要嘅。第二就係話咧，嗰啲人咧，而家我哋好多同事咧，即係或者呢個介人咧，都係可以做到年紀好大嘅，即係佢嘅經驗重要，佢唔係體力啊嘛。咁會唔會可能你哋啊？我唔知你個退休年齡會唔會話都係介係。
喺嗰個行業度繼續即係發光發熱啦。噉我想講講就係話，你如果你面對保險界已經係咁缺乏人人才嘅，而你哋又扯走咁多人，你點樣去處理呢一個可能即係潛在嗰個嗰個嗰個風險咧？噉樣啊，階段招聘。好嘅，主席，分階段招聘呢樣已經係行緊嘅。第二樣嘢咧，其實我亦都。
同業界傾咗咧，就係話做一個叫誒revolving多嘅誒嘅嘅arrangement，即係意思即係話點樣咧？就係請業界咧係由佢哋去推薦一部分特別專業嘅人士咧，係喺短期內咧係借調畀誒保監局咧，係去參與我哋嘅工作。因為我哋知道招聘嘅困難嘅，所以咧其實有啲咩？
嘅意見咧，歡迎各位議員咧係隨時向我哋向我提出。咁咧就誒，尤其是喺喺招聘人手方面嚟講咧，我哋都係同業界都係面對相同嘅困難。但係咧就喺大家支持下啦，我相信咧我哋盡會盡量做好呢樣工作啦。好啊，多謝鄭司。好到依度為止啊，多謝李主席。
係。
亦有一個電腦嘅頭。
投影片嘅作出一個簡介嘅。
儘量用五分鐘之內去完成。
請戴林漢先生咧，就簡介文件。
Thank you, Chairman. Good afternoon, Chairman and honourable members.
Apart from promoting transparency by requiring ESG disclosure.
The exchange should not and cannot make rules that are outside of this legal power to make rules.
Reporting on ESG is also currently linked to risk management and internal controls.
The exchange recognised that an informed market calls for both non-financial and financial information.
given the role and function prescribed by the law, the exchange introduced the ESG guide to focus on issuers' reporting obligations.
for this purpose, the exchange makes listing rules, which are subject to market support, and final approval by the Securities and Futures Commission.
投資者們愈來愈要求知道可能的環境和社會風險，公司可能面臨，以及這些風險如何管理。
Under Section 23 of the Securities and Futures Ordinance, the principal function of the exchange is to provide a fair, orderly and efficient market for the trading of securities.
謝謝你邀請我到立法會議院，向大家介紹有關香港上市公司環境、社會及管治披露要求的最新發展。
The exchanges mandate from the laws that the listing rules reflect currently acceptable standards in the market place and are designed to ensure the listing and the trading of securities are conducted fairly and efficiently, and investors have and can maintain confidence in the market.
環境、和社會。
When formulating listing policies.
這些主題領域contained various ESG aspects.
Rule amendments are made following careful analysis of all the consultation responses.
with respect to ESG， there are a number of mandatory disclosure requirements in Hong Kong.
第一是新公司 ordinance， which came into force in March 2014.
The guide was introduced as a recommended practice and was intended to be the first step in an evolutionary process.
The exchange's first ESG guide came into effect for issuers with financial years ending 31 December 2012.
And in relation to this consultation exercise, we received a total of 203 responses from a broad range of respondents.
The exchange benchmarks the proposed rules against those of other developed markets, and assesses their potential impact on the Hong Kong market.
Following the consultation on the review of the ESG guide in two thousand fifteen, the ESG guide was reorganised into two ESG subject areas.
Following that consultation 2014, we incorporated these companies ordinance requirements into the listing rules and applying to all listed companies.
which mandates that all Hong Kong incorporated companies, unless exempted, include in the business review of their annual directors' reports a discussion of certain environmental and social matters.
在 addition to the new companies ordinance requirements, there are also general obligations of disclosure under the listing rules, and the statutory obligation to disclose inside information under the securities and futures ordinance.
在July 2015，The Exchange published a further consultation paper，proposing to upgrade those obligations to comply and explain，and in December we published our conclusions in relation to that。
在 addition to the reorganisation, all the general disclosure of various ESG aspects under environmental and social subject areas, as well as all the KPIs of different ESG aspects under the environmental subject area, were upgraded from voluntary to comply or explain.
十七。
The exchange adopts a combination of measures to regulate ESG disclosure.
和《》。
它應被 noted that none of the provisions in the GRI is mandatory or subject to comply or explain.
With this in mind, the exchange has organised numerous ESG training events since early 2011.
just to note that corporate governance does not form part of the ESG guide. It's addressed separately in the exchanges corporate governance code.
The information contained in a listing document must be accurate and complete in all material respects, and not be misleading or deceptive.
There are suggestions that the exchange should require ESG disclosure in accordance with the Global Reporting Initiative's G4 Sustainability Reporting Guidelines.
listing applicants are required under listing rules to make disclosures in the form of listing documents, including prospectuses, circulars and any equivalent documents.
The exchange is keenly aware of the need for issuer education in ESG reporting, and believes that it is integral to the wider adoption of ESG reporting.
The development of the ESG guide has been and will continue to be an evolutionary process, with the longer-term goal of achieving better and more comprehensive ESG reporting among issuers.
這些包括mandatory rules， 以及comply or explain provisions和recommended disclosures。 這approach is in line with that adopted by a number of overseas jurisdictions。
Certain other amendments were made to the guide, including revising the introductory section and incorporating general gender diversity into the voluntary provisions of the guide.
在terms of overseas practices， we have reviewed the practices of a number of companies， including Australia， Malaysia， Taiwan and Singapore， and also the EU， mainland China and UK， and believe we are consistent.
研究 indicates that the comply or explain approach is an effective tool to encourage ESG reporting， as the flexibility of the approach， amongst other reasons， enables companies that are just beginning to report， to develop their competency and practices through first-hand experience.
The complier explain requirements are implemented in two phases. The upgrade to the general disclosures come into effect for financial years beginning on or after the 1st of January 2016, and the upgrade in the environmental KPIs for years after 1st of January 2017.
啊！
嗯。
Mr. Graham。
When will you?
process, basically two questions.
Chairman, my colleagues and I would be happy to answer any questions from members. Thank you.
誒，第一位梁繼昌議員。啊，Thank you, Mr. Chairman。啊。
我係監察緊，The implementation of ESG reporting， and I'm one of the respondent in in your consultation.
誒以下咧就開放翻畀誒委員提問題。誒因為時間都緊湊啊，我哋仍然維持誒四分鐘連問連答。
whereby you you're going to review the implementation of new proposal and and when are you planning to move forward with the mandatory disclosure requirement?
Own ESG guide, but but in fact, if the GRI guideline is already there and is you know a widely accepted international standard.
Try to have a review of the implementation of this, you know, disclose or explain, you know, a requirement. Because obviously, I'm obviously thinking about moving ahead with the mandatory disclosure at a later date. Is there any timetable?
哦。
put it out to consultation.
誒，下一位李卓人議。
就哦，得唔得啊？嚇！
我哋最主要個覺得不足嘅地方咧，就係誒喺勞資關係嗰方面。
What we need to do at this stage to alert people to GRI, to make sure that our requirements, where we have requirements, are consistent with GRI, and we have provided that benchmarking exercise of comparing GRI with our requirements.
Of disclosures, which I think will probably take a year or two before we get to that, then I think we would we would do an implementation review. We intend to review and monitor the disclosures against our our requirements as we will do on a sort of annual basis.
And my second question concern about the GRI guidelines, because as you mentioned in page twelve of your PowerPoint, compliance with GRI guidelines not mandatory, but it does serve the purpose to to to you know to help the companies to comply with the exchange.
Would it be more confusing if you know Hong Kong exchange have its own ESG guide? But rather, I think you should highlight or point out what what what the you know exchange you know requirements are comparing with GI, so that you know companies would have an easier time to to to comply with the the EX standard. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you for your questions. I think in terms of the review of implementation, as I explained, the these new provisions under the under the revised ESG guide, they are only just be coming into just coming into effect. So the first set of complier expla
Requirements are only in relation to financial years beginning on or after the 1st of January 2016, so we will only start to see the disclosures around this in the in the short term. I suspect that we don't have a particular time level, but once we have seen a reasonable number of
As to when it's right to move to a mandatory disclosure regime, I think as we've said, we see this as very much an evolutionary process. We do have mandatory disclosure at the very highest level, which we believe is consistent with many other jurisdictions. So, if we are going to move to mandatory, I think it would be.
something that we would obviously have to consult on. We have no immediate plans to do that, having just done this exercise. But clearly, the direction of travel is to move towards more and more comply or explain. And if there are certain provisions which, in the future, it makes sense to be mandatory, then we will certainly consider that and.
In terms of the GRI guidelines, we are we are very express and have been from the beginning that we we do recognise the GRI guidelines. We we do encourage people to to comply with the GRI guidelines or to take note of the GRI guidelines.
And indeed, in our FAQs, we have provided a comparison between GRI and the Exchange Guide, and we've been very specific in drafting our own requirements to make sure that they are consistent where possible with the GRI principles. So I think we're doing.
The time's up.
好。
discuss， but not pass噉啊！
即係例如disclose and pass噉啊，綠燈啦。
係引入一個所謂啲嗯紅綠燈制度啊！
其實你哋會唔會考慮咧？為所有嗰啲上市公司咧？
黃燈唔係藍燈啦，或者誒誒橙燈啦。
誒，第三位係善眾佳園。
Thank you again for your for your question. Maybe I can. I think there are really three different aspects to your to your question. The first is.
就係頭先我所講嘅勞資關係、工傷嘅披露，同埋個供應鏈嘅勞資關係，同埋工傷啊或者啊勞工嘅準則嗰方面嘅披露啊。Mr. Graham。
喂，主席，我提出嘅議程就希望真係提升香港即係嗰個披露嘅要求。咁當然即係我哋知道而家都有個改進啦，即係啊，但係我哋睇到個改進本身，我哋覺得係唔足夠啦。一方面就係即係好多係自願遵守變咗不遵守就解釋。噉我哋覺得不遵守就解釋咧。
yes，我 got it now。Multiple question，yeah，嗯，即係我諗啊，即係公盟提出依一個嘅誒議程咧，就希望即係提升香港誒公司啊企業管治嘅披露嘅要求。咁當然我哋都知道有個改善喺度啦，就但係我哋覺得唔足夠咧，就好多係自願遵守，就變咗。
不遵守就解釋，噉我哋覺得不遵守嘅解釋其實個意義就唔係好大啦。依個第一個問題，第二個頭先梁繼昌都有講到咧，就係我哋希望同誒國際接軌嘅，即係個G Global Reporting Initiative啊，咁希望喺嗰方面係可以完全跟跟進到啦。咁但係我。
即係我哋覺得勞資關係誒嘅風險本身咧，係應該有多啲強制性嘅披露。個風險係包幾方面，第一個就罷工嚇各方面，即係勞資關係會唔會係好惡劣？咁有罷工事件，噉就算嗰時碼頭罷工咧，其實誒對個更
公司影響好大都好啦，都係冇一個好清楚嘅，即係冇個披露嘅嚇。第二樣嘢就係誒，關於工傷嗰方面啲數字啊，啊同埋個工業安全措施嗰方面嘅誒企業嗰個責任啦。噉我哋覺得嗰度亦都應該強制性去誒披露。咁第三方面咧，我哋。
關心到其實而家係好多時勞資糾紛嗰啲問題咧，就唔係直接公司，而係所謂誒而家全世界都關心緊個誒誒supply chain，即係供應鏈。咁好多時向誒任何上市公司咧，佢喺自自己嘅供應鏈裏邊，佢哋有個勞勞資嘅關關係嘅問題。
嚇罷工又好，或者僱用童工嘅問題啊，咁喺個供應鏈嗰方面咧係出咗事，噉我哋覺得喺就算你自己直接僱員冇嘢咧，你個供應鏈下邊出咗事咧，都應該有個強制性披露嘅，咁所以我就想睇下會唔會喺呢方面咧會進一步去改。
Following up in relation to comply or explain, and whether that is sufficient. As I've explained, firstly, I think this is an evolutionary process rather than a revolutionary process. We've moved from voluntary to comply or explain. There is some mandatory overlay to that.
And as I said in my sort of remarks at the beginning, I think it is comply or explain is a well-established process or protocol in relation to matters of this type. And I think my expectation, and I think the the precedent would suggest that people try to comply rather than.
難以解釋，因此它確實有影響。它不是強制性的，但確實有影響，引導他們走向那種立場。但同時，它也意味著他們能夠表達自己的觀點，關於什麼是與他們的業務相關，什麼是需要披露的，以及他們認為什麼不是相關的。他們可以解釋，而不是。
comply, and I think that is the right logical process as we go through this process and educate people around sort of these types of issues. So I think it's a journey, but I think it is a perfectly acceptable and internationally accepted way of moving through this through this process.
嗯。
好嘛？
Mr. Crehan.
分級制度咧。
誒又唔explain，又唔。
People tend to comply rather than explain.
如果唔係，你哋即係你都要諗，你個制度係要accountable to public㗎嘛。
你哋睇下佢嘅解釋係乜嘢，然之後再問佢。公眾知道你，公眾知得乜嘢？
你喺度噉樣樣同佢哋一路對話，公眾冇嘢可以知道嘅喎，除非你問佢嘢，你披露埋啦。
嚇！噉我覺得一個所謂colouring system，一個即係greening system咧，好簡單，公眾可以清楚到究竟佢過唔過關，究竟佢有冇問到，有冇做到噉嘅樣。
即係或者其他顏色啦，跟住咧，好似你哋咁講咧，就係即係唔disclose但係就explain噉樣咧，就係黃燈啦。咁可能有啲咧就。
嗱，你嘅答案咧，其實令唔能夠令我滿意嘅，因為咧，你話覺得冇乜用啊，或者冇乜需要咧，你哋話佢哋解釋咗之後。
誒誒點啊？又唔披露，又唔又唔去解釋嘅咧，就紅燈啦噉樣樣。你哋會唔會考慮咧？嗱，因為你而家仲係做緊seminar啫嘛，你哋會唔會考慮即係你嗰幾百間公司咧，都為佢哋整個？
I mean, I think I mean just what we what we will do in terms of once we see people's disclosures around this. If a company provides decides not to comply but decides to explain, then we will we will look at their explanation, and if we're not satisfied with their explanation.
We will go back and discuss that with the company. I don't think setting up a sort of a public traffic light system. And sorry, we'll go back and we. If we decide they haven't made the right sort of disclosures, we will ask for further disclosure around their explanation. But I don't think setting up a sort of a traffic light
我都係催問。
噉你畀啲咩嘢公眾啊？
我哋，Mr. Graham。
嗰個問，即係追問，正話阿馮家文嗰個問題啦。
即係佢，即係嗰位先生就話咧，即係你咁多對話。
要 disclose all of our discussions as a regulator with a listed company.
即係你話誒，我我宣佈增加多十分鐘啊，因為而家要延長。
因為監管當局佢都唔會披露曬所有嘅對話畀你。誒，下一位係梁國雄議。
咁如果全部都誒披露咧，係唔合唔恰當嘅。我想問，咁有邊個去監管你？
你唔disclose嗰啲communication，你又唔畀一個嘅，你哋對佢哋嘅即係所謂disclosure嘅評估。
in in so far in so far as we have discussions with the company which result in further disclosure being necessary by that company, then the public will know.
needs to be disclosed with the public. It would not be appropriate to disclose all of our discussions with listed companies on the whole range of topics that we have that discussion. Okay.
Miss Graham, at the at the end of the day, we are showing the public that in those circumstances that we are satisfied with the disclosure, in so far as third party. How you how you explain that you are satisfied with the with the
system at this stage for these types of requirements, really you could do that for any type of requirements. I don't think it's particularly necessary, but I but I I do assure you that this is something we will check what types of explanations we get. But as I say, our normal experience in comply or explain is that people.
Insofar as we have discussions as part of our regulatory obligations with companies, we do not make all of those disclosure or discussions public. It would be inappropriate to disclose all of our discussions, which we have on a daily basis, in relation to a whole host of matters around listed companies compliance. Those discussions
Discussion should be between the regulator and the listed company. Insofar as we believe there is additional disclosure that needs to be made to the public, we will require that listed company to do that, and we will do we do that in every area, and we will do it the same in the ESG space. But I do not think it is appropriate to.
With the explanation, that is that is true in everything that we do. Quite clearly, we have a lot of discussions with the companies on a daily basis on a whole host of topics around their disclosure across a whole range of topics, and the only thing that gets disclosed which is appropriate is what we decide.
分散曬。
miss咗佢啊！
誒會。
即係有改有改進啦。
你覺唔覺得應該係？
係邊個監管你啊？你認為應該有人監管你？
所以，在那種sense，我們係accountable to the SFC。
嗱，我我覺得咧，其實咧就有幾樣嘢我都想講嘅，誒。
所以，The SFC conducts an annual audit of the listing function.
嗰個判斷咧，即係話批到幾多？有啲要批到，有啲唔批到。
咁如果你呢個供應鏈嘅管理，如果你唔披露嘅時候，我哋係冇辦法知道㗎嘛。
第一個咧就係關於嗰個供應鏈嘅問題啦，正話啊李啊李李卓仁議員都問咗啦。
即係話，如果供應鏈，因為供應鏈而家誒全球化啦，咁所以所有嘅生產都係。
I think again. I think we have we have disclosures under under our under the comply or explain.
Well, ultimately, ultimately the ultimately the listing the listing function in the exchange is accountable to the SFC.
similarly, we have reporting lines up to the listing committee, which is an independent committee of the of the stock exchange. So, insofar as we are exercising our functions, we are primarily accountable to the SFC in relation to that.
李世權。
再去用翻。
同埋應該有罰則嘅。
我我意見就好簡單啦，因為。
就會要罰，要處罰佢。你覺得啱唔啱？
你仍然為噉係合理啊？如果佢，
如果有強制披露之後，佢唔披露嘅話，
過去嘅制度，噉我我認為唔遵守就解釋嗰個方法咧，係唔唔合理嘅，應該係強制披露嘅。
moved quite considerably forward in the last five years, and as I say, this continues to be a journey. Okay.
誒而家係全球化，我哋應該係盡快同全球嘅誒披露制度，即係嗰個誒係即係接軌嘅。我哋冇可能咧。
If there are certain industries or certain areas where there is a feeling we need more in that space, then that is something we can look at in the future. But it is something that is already focused on in in our general disclosures under the new provisions.
provisions that we have put in, there is a specific element that relates to supply chain management, where there is a general disclosure requirement around the policies on managing environmental and social risks of of the supply chain. So I think we have already highlighted that issue. I think to go
Further at this stage, we also have some other at the moment recommended disclosures around around the supply chain. So I think we have focused on that area. I think we've done sufficient for the moment. As I say, this is an evolutionary process. As we move through that process.
I think I've already explained my position. I think I've explained my position both in relation to GRI, where I've explained they are they are principles, and where we have encouraged people to to adopt that, and where we have borne those in mind as we have developed our own mandatory and complyer.
In answer to your second question, I do believe that the comply or explain regime is an appropriate regime for us at the moment. As I say, we have a combination of mandatory requirements, comply or explain requirements and voluntary requirements. That, to my mind, is consistent.
Mr. Graham。
張華豐副主席。
即要披露畀投資者知咧。
啊，主席啊，我都想跟。
公司，是某啲嘅，我們應該歡迎。
跟進咧嚇，淨係解釋完就解釋完啦，即係冇跟進咧。呢呢度我想知道清楚啲。
information or other material information that is needed to be disclosed, the same requirements apply to suspended companies as they do to non-suspended companies.
question, as we go through the next twelve or eighteen months and we begin to see people's disclosures, we can make an assessment under an implementation review. But it's too early to make that judgement. Have to take more experience. Yes, exactly.
With international practice and international precedent, and is also I think appropriate for Hong Kong at the stage we are at in terms of developing our ESG guidelines. You have to remember that we had no guidelines in this space before about 2011 and 2012. So we have.
啊！主席啊，我哋將披露嘅責任咧提升到咧不遵守就解釋啊。咁呢個制度已經實施咗大大半年啦。我想問問有咩效果，有咩效果可以見到出嚟咧？同埋喺呢段時間有幾多個case啊？需要解釋嘅咧？咁解釋之後，解釋之後，我哋有冇？
Thank you for your question. I think as I as I explained, although the consultation conclusions were published some six or so months ago, the actual upgrade only comes into effect for financial years beginning on or after the first of January two thousand and sixteen. So we're only now.
Basically, for most companies, that means companies whose year end is the thirty-one st of March two thousand and sixteen. So we're only now beginning to see the reporting requirements that were imposed by that new regime. So I think it's too early to answer your question. So I think we will, as I answered in relation to the earlier.
我都想跟進啦，即係特別係嗰啲停牌嗰啲公司，嗰啲好似嗰停牌公司嘅股份，嗰啲投資者非常心急啊！即係無所適從。咁到底我哋咧同公司啊去聽佢解釋之後，我哋有幾多可以披露，有幾多可唔要披露咧？呢個係咪要定喺一個？
個一個level一個水準，否則咧你講完之後就完全咧唔可以同投資者披露一啲內內邊嘅問題，咁個投資者無所適從嘅噃，係咪？噉係唔係即係特別對呢啲停牌嘅係即係同個公司誒解釋之後咧，都仲要有一部分信息。
We seem to be on a slightly different topic, but to answer your question in relation to suspended companies, the obligations to make disclosures in relation to suspended companies are exactly the same as in relation to companies which are currently not suspended on the stock exchange. So, insofar as there is insight.
of criticism.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments. Much appreciated. Yeah. Okay. Oh. Thank you for your.
誒，亦都多謝各位委員誒積極嘅參與同埋一路工作上嘅支持。噉啊，冇其他事項嘅話，我宣佈散會。係。
係咪？Thank you very much. Okay. Thank you.誒，我哋結束咗最後一項㗎啦。噉就今日呢個議事嘅會議咧，係事務委員會嘅本屆最後一次會議。
好，最後一位係石禮謙議員。誒，Thank you, David. Well, I want you to leave here. This is not a one-sided criticism of the present system. I think the any any any measures that aim to improve governance of companies, particularly less
And I look forward to seeing how the whole process of evolutionary process, rather than a revolutionary over-regulated process, being implied. Which I think you have my support here, and probably you have the support of the market. Which a lot of the listed companies of which I sit in, they come, they.
Looking forward to making this disclosure. My colleague Christopher Jones just now, he he understood that this is a ESG disclosure, not a a a regulatory disclosure. That's a different issue. But the question he likes to bring in at this moment is this.
他asked the question: Is that the public also have a right to know when they, when some listed company which they invested in, and when they were being delisted or put into a situation when trading is not being allowed, that at least they must have some information? That was what his
This question is about not that his misunderstand us. This is the ESG disclosure, so I think if you take that into consideration, I think it's quite important. I share his view that everybody have a right to understand. But also, I like to criticise my colleague, some of my colleagues who make earlier questions.
particularly林鄭綱，as he was the chairman of the SFO Bill， he should know better what is to be disclosed and not to be disclosed. You can't disclose everything. Companies do also have the rights and this is what we call the insider information. At what level that that information to be disclosed? Worse comes
Words they can go go for a safe harbour. I think, but what you are adopting here, you have my support and the support of quite a majority of the companies which are going in. So please don't leave here with with the some of my colleagues from the opposition side to criticise. But they are here just to criticise for the.